All right.
So my mate keen said it
quite last minute would you paper for this conference.
And I said I'm really busy.
I've been a struggle to pay for together and a struggle to kind of like talk about
desk engineering and doing it.
So I thought, I submit this no chance.
Fortunately or unfortunately, we're doing this one.
So I'm going to talk about bipolar disorder, what living with
it has required me to learn to become aware of.
And then I'm going to talk about the idea of regulators and dysregulated.
So these are things that can change or alter your stay physically or mentally.
These are a lot of ideas that have been in my head for a long time, which is why
I chose this topic, because I thought I could probably put something together,
probably not talk about it very well, but at least talk about it authentically.
So here we go.
Just a bit of a disclaimer.
Mental health. It's a complex topic.
Be kind to each other.
We don't know what other people are living through or going through.
Be kind to yourself.
If you're not sure about yourself or friends or others towards
a medical professional, or talk to this marathon's very good as well.
So I said it's about.
So when I was diagnosed with bipolar disorder,
I didn't agree with the diagnosis and I didn't understand it
because I thought I polar was kind of like this,
you know, you're a little bit up, you're a little bit down.
That was my understanding of bipolar disorder, and that was not
what was happening with my life or my experiences or my symptoms.
They were far more complex or far more chaotic.
There were things that had happened.
I didn't understand what he did.
He didn't really remember.
So what I learned is that bipolar disorder
can sometimes be more like this, where you can appear well
and going through normal states or these states can get very,
very, very intense both up and down and very chaotic.
And then it can all kind of normalize again.
So this is it.
This is what it is.
It's more disordered.
And these higher states can be very extreme.
They can be hypomanic which is just often high energy
not sleeping, lots of pressure talking this sort of thing.
They can go into mania, which is prolonged periods of severe impulsive behavior,
damaging behavior, complex behavior, and it can go
all the way to psychosis in its most extreme forms.
In the lower zones, it can be very similar to unipolar depression,
and it can be similar to major depression or treatment resistant depression.
And all of these states are complex states to be in.
So that's what I learned.
Bipolar could be.
I also learned it could be like this.
This would be what type one bipolar might look like.
So type two bipolar, which is prolonged periods of severe depression
followed by a kind of uplift in state and then potentially an extreme
uplifting state again into manic episodes or psychotic episodes.
And you can
appear well for a lot of the time
could also be like this.
This could be something like type one bipolar disorder, where people
are in a kind of fairly level state, and then long, prolonged,
intense periods of severe mania or psychosis.
So it's complex.
And one of the challenges is that you often appear
well when you're managing bipolar well, but you can also get very, very ill.
So it can be it can also add to the challenge of living with the condition.
So all in all, what is bipolar disorder?
I don't know, I did a little bit of research.
It's highly heritable.
It's about 70% inherited.
It destabilizes mood regulation compromises limbic system regulation.
You have hypersensitivity sensitivity to dopaminergic effects
which can affect addiction.
There's intercellular signaling stuff that goes on, which is why things like
lithium, which is a heavy metal, can actually help treat bipolar disorder.
There's all sorts of circadian biology.
There's a there's the effect that's called kindling.
So kindling is the word you use to start to fire.
Kindling means that often more people have people will have episodes which
are clearly caused by a significant event, but each episode is degenerative.
Each episode damages the brain's neural pathways, meaning that later events
may seem to be completely unrelated to the external environment.
So untreated bipolar is a degenerative disorder.
I hesitated to mention these numbers because they're horrifying,
but 1 in 3 people with bipolar disorder will attempt suicide,
and untreated 1 in 5 people will complete suicide.
So bipolar disorder is a severely complex and damaging and difficult condition.
I hesitated to mention the numbers because they're shocking and upsetting,
but also, I think it was important to do justice to the reality
that some of people are living with.
So living with bipolar disorder means managing this regulation
and also what you call wellness management.
So medication is the first part of this.
So medication is going to try and limit these peaks and these troughs.
So this is done by mood stabilizers.
That will be the foundation of most treatments which will stabilize mood
as it sounds like it could also be sedatives.
It could be antidepressants.
Antidepressants can trigger mania.
So it might be antidepressants combined with antipsychotics.
Going on to mood stabilizers can take months
because you titrate slowly to monitor side effects.
And it may take multiple attempts as there are different drugs
and they work very, very different with different people.
So building a medication regime takes a long time.
It takes a long time to establish a regime like this.
And while you're doing that, you're essentially unmedicated
or partly medicated.
So these are difficult times.
However, when you get on to a medication regime, you often
then have the ability to adjust for yourself
to kind of manage your own state based on what's going on around you.
The next hugely
important thing about bipolar disorder treatment is support its other people.
So who are the people you trust to know about your condition
and the symptoms of your condition?
And who are the people you will give the agency to say?
You can tell me when I appear unwell and you can tell me
from my wellness plan what I've said I should be doing.
Maybe it's adjusting medication or stopping travel.
And also you may give some of these people agency to say,
if I don't make the changes that I've said when I'm well, I will do.
I'm giving you the agency to take control away from me.
And you do this and you do this in advance
so that the trauma of that experience is less afterwards.
It can be traumatic to have freedom taken away from you.
But if you've agreed in advance that this is the consequence
of not following your wellness plan, then that gives you a better pathway
to recover from some of these experiences.
So support is an essential part of medication.
Medication on its own without support
typically fails, and typically a lot of relapse.
Support also can be therapy.
It can be doing things like dealing with grief.
Grief comes from loss.
With bipolar disorder, you have loss of agency.
You have loss of self.
You have loss from the experiences that can happen,
hypomanic or manic states can lead to a lot of harm.
They can damage relationships.
You can spend lots of money.
You can do very impulsive or risky or dangerous things.
All of these things have to be processed and may involve processing
grief and processing your relationships and how you feel about things.
So support and psychotherapy and the people around you is essential.
And one of the most effective treatments for bipolar disorder is a regime called
interpersonal social relationship therapy,
which is about understanding yourself and the people around you and
trying to regulate.
So. Now
we're going to regulation, which is a key part of this topic.
So regulation is we've got medication.
We've got the support of the people around us.
But regulation is something that you can do for yourself.
This is when you try to manage the the kind of red lines,
which are the things that destabilize you and counterbalance them
with these green lines, which are the things that will stabilize you.
It's a very active form of treatment.
You have to kind of commit to doing it.
You have to take action.
You have to make changes.
If you're someone, for example, who I don't know, there's a flight attendant
that means that you're changing time zones, a lot of changing time zones.
A lot is actually very dangerous for bipolar disorder
because it causes sleep to sleep issues.
And dysregulated sleep is one of the biggest causes of mania or hypomania.
So it's assets and your ability to engage in these activities
when you're in an altered state is also compromised.
If you're very depressed, it can be difficult to do things that lift.
If you're very manic, you don't necessarily want to come down,
you're compromised.
You have a compromise sense of intersection.
So perception is your understanding of what's around you in terror
is your understanding of yourself, your internal self, your state.
And compromised interoception is one of the symptoms of bipolar disorder.
I don't know how we're doing.
Any time.
Could be good, could be bad.
If it's bad, I'll go to the bathroom.
So common regulators and dysregulated is the first one is sleep.
Sleep is one of the most important, essential things to get right.
Dysregulated sleep is the biggest trigger for hypomania.
Hypomania will cause more dysregulated sleep, which will be a trigger for mania.
By the time you're manic,
you're not sleeping, potentially not for days, sometimes people for weeks.
And that can be the path towards even more severe
states like psychosis, followed by by a big crash.
So sleep, hugely important.
And managing sleep might mean changing your job.
So I used to live in Singapore.
I used to travel to Australia
at the beginning of the week, sometimes to India at the end of the week.
That's a lot of time zone shifting, incredibly bad for managing sleep, and I
had to change the nature of the work that I was doing to to account for that.
The next one is rhythm.
So we're incredibly embodied creatures,
and our psychological state is intimately tied to our physical state.
So when you eat, when you sleep, when you talk to other people,
when you do exciting things, when you do calming things,
all of these things are about rhythm when you exercise and so on.
A predictable cycle of rhythm is for everyone,
a way to stay very, very healthy.
And disruption to rhythm is a very easy way to become dysregulated again.
Interpersonal social relationship theory therapy is.
And social rhythm therapy, I mean, is all about managing rhythm
and all about managing processing things with other people.
Stress, unsurprisingly, is a big dysregulated.
Stress can require interventions and changing things.
Stress comes from chaos, from conflict, but it can also come from excitement.
It can come from achieving goals.
It can come from big changes.
But stress is hard to manage, especially in this world now,
which will be the next part of the talk.
The world of AI, the world of stressful AI.
I keep pressing the button for the next pieces.
Sorry about that. Substance says okay.
So substance use disorder in bipolar is very, very, very, very high.
One of the highest for any psychological condition, psychiatric condition.
That might be because people are self-medicate with substances
to control mood, but they will often have a backlash.
But also the pharmacology that you're dealing with,
the the medication you're taking, these are also substances as well.
So they can be regulators, they can be dysregulated, as most people
or many people with bipolar disorder will suffer from substance use disorder.
And management of that can be very, very important.
Next you have awareness.
So the more aware you are of your states, the more aware you are of how you're
feeling and also the symptoms and so on is a way to manage your condition.
It's also awareness of the fact that things can get very, very bad,
but hopefully they will also get better and more episodes you have.
The more you realize that you can recover from them,
and that they don't necessarily mean it's the end.
People are regulators.
Sometimes people who know about who you care about,
who you can be your authentic self with.
But people can also be dysregulated as people can be chaotic,
family can be chaotic.
Friends can be helpful.
Friends can not be helpful.
So people is an important part of this.
But again, they can be a source of conflict and instability
therapy and integration.
So this is the other part we spoke about briefly before.
So how you therapy is how you talk through experiences.
And then integration is how do you process the things that have happened.
We all need to integrate complex experiences
grief, conflict, excitement, achievement, whatever.
These experiences need to be integrated for us to be able to kind of continue.
Otherwise, you build a backlog of stuff that you haven't processed
and become very scattered, very disjointed and very unfocused.
There are some other surprising things as well that are regulators or dysregulated.
Goal attainment is known to be quite dysregulated.
It's an exciting event, but it can also lead to unknowns afterwards.
It's a big change.
Change is complex to deal with, so goal achievement can be challenging.
Changes to your foundational beliefs can also be dysregulated.
And AI is doing a lot of that.
And that will be a bit of a theme of what we talk about a little bit afterwards.
Antidepressant.
You would have thought good for managing depression, but they're bad for mania.
So, you know, these things are not necessarily simple.
Sunny days can be dysregulated because it can affect circadian rhythm.
We don't get a lot of sunny days in the UK, so maybe that's the right
place to be.
But the longer days, the shorter days,
all of these things can affect sleep and it can't be overestimated.
How much sleep is important.
Intense exercise.
The other one is pregnancy.
So typically when people are pregnant, they won't be able to take
mood altering medication. And that's really, really hard.
That's a tremendous challenge for people going through pregnancy.
Postpartum can be complex as well.
Again, we're very we are embodied creatures.
The hormones that go through us, whether it's through excitement
or pregnancy or whatever, can change our states enormously.
So all of these different things are happening.
And the risks when you get into different states can be extremely severe.
So what ends up happening is you kind of go through this and start
to understand it and learn about it is what I've called
pathology happiness. So
when you're starting to get more happy, more excited,
having more fun, getting more engaged with things, really, really getting
into things, you start to pathologies that am I going into hypomania?
Am I going into mania?
Am I overexcited by this and my overstimulated by this?
Am I losing myself in this too much?
Is this a safe place to be?
Do I need to downshift?
Do I want to downshift because this feels like a great place to be?
Hypomania is an incredibly exciting
and it's awful to say, but wonderful state to be in.
You're happy, you make friends, you care about the people around you.
All new experiences are exciting rather than frightening.
You're creative.
You're doing more exercise. You're seeing more people.
So you don't want to avoid being in states that make you happy.
But you also know that these states can lead to worse states.
So you pathologies constantly.
You're always monitoring what's around you, always monitoring how you're feeling.
And if you've ever gotten into a state of monitoring, am I feeling happy?
How am I feeling happy? Am I feeling too happy?
That itself is quite anxiety inducing in a bit of shit, so
you often end up getting quite depressed from that, because this constant attention
and this constant checking into states is a sort of manic thing,
and it's not a particularly happy state to be in.
So you ask yourself.
Am I shutting myself out from the outside world?
Am I not having the social contact that I used to have
and my beliefs changing enormously?
And that's when I'm going to transition now into AI,
because talking to lots of people in the world of AI,
engineering or whatever, there's a lot of this change
in state excitement, but also lack of focus and so on.
So that's going to be kind of the theme of what we talk about next,
what the this regulators are that I'm hyper aware of and that I see
in the world of AI and sort of reflect on how it feels for myself.
But I also see these states in other people.
I see other people in states that feel grandiose
or hypomanic or overexcited or disconnected.
I see a lot of behavior around me, which is exciting.
I also see behavior which is maladaptive, and if it was me performing
that behavior,
I would actually be concerned and be thinking about what do I need to do
to downshift and control this and intervene on this one?
So there we go.
Bin pathologies, everything.
The world of AI people are changing.
The way people are acting is changing.
The way people are focusing or the way people are collaborating is changing.
So what are some of the dysregulation or the things that can just regulate?
So the first one I worked at a therapist called Margot Forum,
and she has a severe type one bipolar disorder.
And one of the things she told me that was quite surprising
is that foundational changes in your core beliefs can be profoundly dysregulated.
So she went on a kind of four day meditation retreat.
There was a very intense experience for her.
It was followed immediately by a severe psychotic episode.
Five minutes left
AI itself.
The way it's changing us is dysregulated.
It's changing our beliefs. So how do you deal with this?
I'm going to go a bit faster now, and maybe skip
through a few of the less interesting ones.
You have to integrate experiences.
How do you feel about this? Is it making you happier?
Is it making you less happy? Is it changing your behavior?
Addiction?
I won't go into this too much.
Then the short cycle dopamine loop a lot of people have spoken about with AI.
It is very, very addictive to have this fast reward mechanism.
There's lots of material out there about how to deal with addiction.
People with bipolar disorder are much more likely to suffer from addiction
grandiosity.
I'm going to spend less time on that one,
because I think I have a better section that talks about this.
This one I'll talk about, in my own way, aggression
and competitiveness, a symptom of these highly elevated states.
The world of AI is pretty aggressive.
So I read an article by someone saying, like, I've asked a bunch of people
in my organization, I've only got space for the 100 X developers.
Everyone else is not as important.
Now that's pretty aggressive.
These 100 X developers, are they the best developers or are they
just the most noisy ones who are saying that no one else is collaborating?
This capitalist environment we're in actually fosters
aggression and competition.
So how do you deal with that?
Have empathy with other people?
Don't don't fight them. How are they feeling?
Are they enjoying this world and also have fun?
Not everything has to be competitive.
We're supposed to enjoy our lives.
Attentional.
So a great grind. Poor band.
It means death by a thousand cuts.
I'm going to briefly talk about this because you probably know about it.
Your attention just gets destroyed.
Short cycle work that you're doing.
Being able to work on everything kills your attention.
We're constantly multitasking.
I think most of us are feeling things like this.
So how do you deal with it? Focus.
Creating space for the work that you're doing.
Running tasks to completion.
Recognizing when you're engaging in displacement activities.
Prioritizing.
Creating protected, time
pressured speaking.
Wolfs get past this one,
except for the fact that your AI speaks to you like someone who's on cocaine.
It's like nonstop doesn't listen.
No space to interruptions. That's pressured speaking.
It's awful to listen to.
What's even more awful is when a bunch of your colleagues
take all the pressure speaking from their AI
and throw it at you, and then you're like, God, it's coming from all directions.
So what do we do about that compressed signal to noise?
Like, what's the high level message? What should this mean?
Not what's the 30 pages of stuff that is your stream of consciousness
that I don't necessarily want to see?
So this is the key one.
I'm interested in maladaptive creativity.
So this is going to get a bit philosophical mental model.
On the left is me building a system my my model of it mental model on the right.
In the middle is the system itself similar but different.
Next mental model is the model my colleague has.
They're slightly different, but they're sort of roughly in sync.
Because we talk a lot, we make small changes.
We have to look at what we've written.
Now, when AI does a lot of this for you and it does it very fast,
the mental models start to look like this.
One person can create this palace of stuff.
They don't really necessarily know what's in it.
What they've created is very different to their mental model.
The mental model from the person who is trying to understand
it is even more different when people say to me, you don't need
to review pull requests, you don't need to review specs.
That's that's wrong.
You do, because it's not about quality control.
It's about engaging with the mental model so that they can see what someone
has built and how it works.
Because part of my job and your jobs is also
to understand that system so that we can fix it and maintain it.
This is the hardest thing to manage, but it's the thing that I think
will help people the most.
So you share, you collaborate, you build your models together.
So here we go.
Bipolar disorder, dysregulation and AI challenges,
but also things that you can do about it.
I'll finish now with some awful things.
I brainstorm some of this with AI if I write everything myself by hand.
But it came up, it was riffing on some ideas.
Tokens are cocaine.
Okay, not very sensitive.
How I learned to stop shipping and love the spec and kind of.
All right.
Hypomania driven development.
Very tasteless.
Really tasteless engineering with a brain on fire.
The magic and madness of agentic engineering.
Thoughtless.
And then this one.
Three agents for work.
Trees, two laptops, no sleep code shipped.
Marriage didn't all caps.
When I said this is all shit, it said.
Lesson noted.
Drop drug metaphors drop wonder framing on psychological topics.
I treat them with care.
So that's it.
Thank you. Thanks for your attention.
Thank you so much
for honest, very exposed to talk.
That was hugely interesting.
Somebody who devoted myself as well.
So I went to yes,
there is a lot of stress out there that works and models for anything to do.
So does anybody have any questions.
Can we get a look at this.
Or I can repeat the question
if that makes it easier.
I'll start again.
You talked about transforming your court release
being quite dysregulated.
I'm wondering whether
that includes things like sort of moments of resolution
in sort of if you're working
in science or something creative,
when you're a bit flips in your head and you see the world differently.
I mean, to me those moments are almost what I live for.
I think just they feel brilliant.
But is that the kind of thing that you're talking about?
Well, it's exactly that.
It can feel brilliant. It can feel like everything has changed.
There's so much scope to do different things.
It leads to that real, real excitement that can kind of take you down
these paths. It's not to say that they're bad.
Once you've had these beliefs changed, you might learn a lot more
and know a lot more.
It's just that that's likely going to be
counterbalanced with how do you integrate that?
How has the world changed for me?
Am I at peace with that?
What's my role in this new world?
So none of these things are necessarily intrinsically bad, but they may require
that kind of counterbalance of space afterwards.
Thank you.
Should I go?
You talked about collaboration, and working with
LLMs and agents is inherently very solo activity.
Have you found any good ways to
build in collaboration into workflows?
Yeah.
So at the divergent stage where you're thinking about lots of ideas,
maybe that's something that's solo.
When you've got your ideas and you're starting to think about
turning it into a specification or a plan, that's
when you move into a convergent phase with another person.
I've had these ideas.
How can we narrow the aperture? Aperture?
Sorry, I work at McKinsey,
so how can we narrow that down to something that we can understand?
And also can we do a hand off?
You came up with the idea you've built the specification with me.
I'll move to the implementation.
Well, you then take the implementation
and tell me if it's okay and if it's ready to be integrated.
The fact that AI can offload
toil should actually mean that we get more space to collaborate.
So all of my standups are one hour because we don't need to go through
the small bitty things.
We can use it as kind of pair
programing or pair specifying sessions or to talk over these things.
So I think there are some techniques, but I think it's the biggest challenge
that I see in terms of the tech world we're in, the breakdown of collaboration.
Yeah. Thank you.
Have you
found or would you be able to share any specific prompts
or maybe agents or things that would help you
or us regulate our mood and,
you know, sort of control our, our feelings?
I, I mean, I'm using AI mostly to build software,
but for me, what's important to regulate is more how I do that.
I do it in the mornings.
That's my creative time.
I rarely have my laptop open from about 5:00 onwards
and I won't be doing creative work then.
At that point, I need to be kind of
transitioning down into a state where I'm less stimulated.
So some of this is about saying to AI, don't give me lots of information,
give me some more pieces and I will direct where we go next.
Other parts of it are simply about when you decide to switch off and say,
I'm not going to listen anymore, I need time to kind of go
away, calm myself down, and then I'll come back to it tomorrow.
So creating space, but also creating friction, which is also
how people manage addiction, is to create friction in systems.
And. Yeah, that's that's fine.
I don't reset advice.
So when you are in the going to day day.
Thanks for.